Walter and Florence Lasinski collection CPAA 05.18
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Walter and Florence Lasinski collection
1893-2010
CPAA 05.18
Connecticut Polish American Archives
10.5 Linear feet
Walter and Florence Lasinski were historians of the Polish National Catholic Church (PNCC) and Polish American life. They resided in New Jersey and were members of the PNCC, a reformed Roman Catholic Church started by Francis Hodur in 1897 in Scranton, Pennsylvania. The collection includes extensive information about parishes (past and present) and clergy members in the PNCC from its creation.
Walter, Lasinski
Arrangement note
Series 2 & 3: While originally organized alphabetically by town and parish by Walter Lasinski, collection was rearranged for research efficiency purposes by state and alphabetically by town within that state.
Biographical/Historical note
Walter H. Lasinski Walter Lasinski was born on February 17, 1923 in Bayonne, New Jersey. He served in the U.S. Army from 1943 to 1946 as a sergeant in World War II. He attended Union College in Cranford, New Jersey from 1960 to 1967. During his life, he was an industrial instrumentation instructor for the Exxon Company in Bayonne, NJ (1941-83) and an administrator and researcher for the Commission on History and Archives of the Polish National Catholic Church in Scranton, PA. He married Florence Kopczynski in 1948 in Bayonne and they had two children; Paul and Raymond. He was given many honors including a service award from the PNCC Music Commission in 1980 and a Certificate of Appreciation from the Polish American Historical Association in 1991. Lasinski passed away on May 27, 2010.
Polish National Catholic Church (PNCC) The Polish National Catholic Church began in 1897 when Father Hodur had the first mass at St. Stanislaus in Scranton, Pennsylvania. The creation was a reaction to problems many Polish Catholics had with the Catholic hierarchy in the United States. Hodur wanted parishioners more included in the church, such as with the approval of priests, appointment of Polish bishops as representatives of their ethnicity, governance of the individual churches by the parishioners, and use of the Polish language during services. Other changes were that priests could marry, the sole power of the Pope was not recognized, and the preaching and listening to the Word of God was considered sacramental. At the first synod in 1904, the church officially disassociated themselves with the Roman Catholic Church (RCC). By 1907, membership grew to more than 15,000 people. The creation and growth was not easily done however. There was much resistance towards the PNCC including violence towards bishops. In 1923, the publication of Rola Boża (God’s Field) spread the message of the church to all followers. With fewer people learning Polish, the General Synod approved the use of English in the Mass. In 1984, a dialogue was initiated between the PNCC and RCC to repair strained relations. They agreed on limited intercommunion. With growth in membership of up to 130,000 by 1953, numbers have dropped to less than 10,000 according to a 2009 census of parishes.
Father Franciszek (Francis) Hodur Hodur was born on April 1, 1866 to Jan and Maria Hodur in Zarki, Chrzanow, Poland. He began school at the age of ten due to the prolonged closing of the only school in his town. At the age of thirteen, he enrolled in St. Anne's High School in Krakow. In 1889, he graduated from St. Anne's and enrolled in the Theology Program at Jagiellonian University. While there, he was an activist for peasant rights, education and economic improvement, and better living conditions. The administration accused him of insubordination so he left for the United States. Upon arrival, he advertised himself in newspapers. Father Benvenuto Gramplewicz of Nanticoke, Pennsylvania brought him to the Scranton Diocese as there was a shortage of Polish speaking clergy. He was then sent to St. Vincent's Benedictine Archabbey in Latrobe, Pennsylvania. After studying for additional months, he returned to Scranton where he was ordained to the priesthood by Bishop William O' Hara in 1893.
His first assignment was Scranton's Polish Sacred Heart of Jesus and Mary Parish. In addition to clergy duties, he also involved himself and his parishioners in activities such as Polish patriotic programs, plays, a parish library, and editing a newspaper. In 1895, he was assigned as pastor to Holy Trinity Parish in Nanticoke, PA. In 1897, after a rebellion by the parish towards their controlling priest, Hodur was requested by the people to become the pastor at the newly reformed St. Stanislaus parish in Scranton. He accepted and celebrated the first Mass there, thus starting the Polish National Catholic Church. As a result, he was excommunicated from the Roman Catholic Church in 1898. In his new parish he cared for many of the Polish immigrants experiencing adversity. He remained in this parish for fifty-six years. During that time he established the newspaper Straż, traveled to Rome to make a plea to reform the church, founded the organization "Spójnia", became a bishop, and expanded the church greatly.
Preaching until eight days before his death, Hodur was blind for years and physically weak from diabetes. He died on February 16, 1953 in Scranton.
Polish National Union The Polish National Union of America (PNU) was also known as Spójnia. It was a not-for-profit fraternal society founded in 1908 by Father Hodur. The headquarters were located in Scranton, PA and was affiliated with the PNCC. Its members were provided with life insurance, mortgages, retirement plans, and a credit union. It was created as an organization for PNCC men due to the discrimination against them from other Polish American fraternal societies affiliated with the Roman Catholic Church. They published the newspaper “Straż” (The Guard) starting in 1897. There are more than 100 branches which participate in many activities such as charitable events, scholarships to children of members, tours of Poland, and youth retreats.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains information about The Polish National Catholic Church, Rev. Francis Hodur, other clergy members, correspondence and research done by Walter Lasinski, individual PNCC parishes in the United States, defunct parishes, and the first Polish settlement in the U.S. at Panna Maria, TX. The years range from 1900-2010.
Florence, Lasinski; Catholics -- Polish; Correspondence.; Polish Americans -- Religious life; Polish Americans -- Texas -- Panna Maria -- History; Polish National Catholic Church of America; Polish National Catholic Church of America -- Bishops -- Biography; Polish National Catholic Church of America -- History; Polish National Catholic Church of America -- Pennsylvania -- Scranton; Polish National Union of America; Polish people -- United States
- General Information about PNCC, Bishop Hodur, and other Bishops., 1905-2010; This series contains general information about the Polish National Catholic Church, founder Francis Hodur, and other Bishops..
  - Polish National Catholic Church- Information and visuals of flag and emblem; national anthem(s) of Poland., 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Constitution and Laws of the PNCC., 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - PNCC directories (1927-2006); “Immigration, ‘Americanization’ and the P.N.C.C.” Rev. Dr. Czeslaw Kuliczkowski (2006); “Ustawy Czyli (1916); “Closed Parishes of the Eastern Diocese of the Polish National Catholic Church” (2008)., 1927-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hodur- Biographical Information Part 1: Assorted biographies from encyclopedias, dictionaries, biography books, articles, and essays, 1930; 1954-1977; 1991-2003, 1930-2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hodur- Biographical Information Part 2: Books: Z Dziejow Liceum Nowodworskiego W Polsce Ludowe,Ks. Franciszek Hodur, A Short History on the Life and Struggles of Bishop Francis Hodur (2), Pięć Nauk; Information about St. Vincent Archabbey; Information about Juliusz Słowacki, 1889; 1954; 2000-2009., 1889-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hodur- Publications and articles: “Straż”, “Rola Boża”, “American Polonia Reporter”, “Deacon’s Blog”, & “God’s Field”; newsletters, 1905; 1938; 1963-66; 2000-2009., 1905-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hodur- Primary source documents: photos; articles; bishop election form, 1900; Ellis Island records for travel; 1893; 1916; 1933-48. Anniversary of birth/death documents, 1993-2009., 1893-2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hodur- Writings, lectures, 1906-1935. History of the PNCC: Articles, essays, timeline, pamphlet, internet articles, Directory of history departments, organizations, and historians from American Historical Association, small books, 1965-2005., 1906-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Hodur information- Publications (A History of the Polish Women’s Alliance of America), Walter Lasinski correspondence, specific parish histories, Abraham Lincoln article, University of Krakow and Nowodworski Foundation information, various articles, 1948; 1987-2009., Bulk, 1987-2009; 1948-2009 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Polish National Union- Lists of branches and information about Spójnia and “Straż”, 1910-2008. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brief information on Huntington Station, NY; Pulaski Rd, Pulaski Day articles and information; Miscellaneous articles, essays, information, 1915; 1934; 1996-2009., 1915-2009 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Quotes- Part 1. 94 famous Poles, 261 pages, from internet sources. Includes brief biography on individuals., 2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Quotes- Part 2., 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Reverend Anthony Iwuc; One photo with Cardinal Król of Philadelphia., 1950-1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mistrzyni klawesynu (Master of harpsichord) articles about Wanda Landowska., 2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Przebudzenie (Awakening): October 14, 1928 (p. 3, 19-22); October 21, 1928 (3, 21-22); October 28, 1928 (3, 7-8); November 4, 1928 (3, 7-9) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - “The Declaration of Scranton.”, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence- Lasinski: Wladyslaw Pietrzyk, Paul Gruginski, Joseph Cyman, Sandra Dobrovolskis, James Konicki, Joseph Wieczerzak, and miscellaneous., 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Genealogy information, copies of photos and documents., 1861; 1890; 1965; 2009 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sacrament of Matrimony., 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bayonne, New Jersey PNCC research., 1904 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - PNCC general information., 2006-2010 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Purchase decision to buy Polish National Union building., 2009 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence & articles, 2004-2009 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Leo Kowalski (author)- Correspondence, book reviews, small biographies, 2009. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ramzi Musallam- Arabic Catholic Church in Milford, CT: Correspondence (questions about ordination, association to Reformed Catholic Church), about the church, autobiography., 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 4 CDs: Spójnia power point presentation for the youth of the PNCC, 2004; Kenny G; PNCC speakers. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kopczynski (Among the founders of the PNCC)- Family history: Photograph: Frank & John Kopczynski and mother; family group sheet, 1994; History from library catalog, 1992; National Archive microfilm, 1891; money order receipt, 1938; Bayonne, NJ city directory, 1914; photos, articles relating to wedding and anniversary in 1953; composition book, 1924; correspondence & family tree, 1998; articles, 2005-2006, prayer cards, medal., 1891-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Brodzinkski- Change of name document for John Brodzinski, 1929; Bayonne, NJ directory, 1914, 1918, 1922; Application for marriage (Paul Brodzinski & Anna Badaczewska), 1893; marriage & baptismal records, articles, 1940; photos; discharge certificate for John S. Brodzinski from army, 1940; funeral arrangements for John Brose, 1959; bank account information, 1958-1959., 1893-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - “Biskupi Naszego Kosciola” (Bishops of our Church, part 1) in God’s Field., 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - “Biskupi Naszego Kosciola” (Bishops of our Church, part 2) in God’s Field., 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writings regarding sacrament, ordination of women, etc in PNCC- Tidings of Holy Name of Jesus National Catholic Parish, 2009; Deacon’s Blog, 2007; Wydanie Jubiluszowe, 1922; 100th anniversary celebration of The Sacrament of the Word of God, 2009; Various articles, 2009; God’s Field. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Biography of Joseph René Vilatte, 2000 (French, first independent Catholic Bishop in North America); other articles & photos, 2009., 2000-2009 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Biskupi Naszego Kosciota, 2009. Compiled and edited by Boguslaw Janiec, Scranton, PA. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Information on PNCC bishops- Joseph F. Padewski, Thaddeus Peplowski,Francis Hodur, Anthony D. Kopka., 2001-2008 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous articles- Straz, Newark Advertiser, 1905 (regarding support for Poland); Ameryka- Echo, 1906; 2000-2008. All mentioning Newark, NJ and Hodur., 1905-2008 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Padewski- Photos: Life, clergy, Tittmoning Internment Camp, Rakowiecka Prison., Bulk, 1930-1945; 1930-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Padewski- Photos: Self portraits and burial place., Bulk, 1923-1951; 1923-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Padewski- Lasinski correspondence and research, 2005-2007; 17 pages of translation for Padewski Project, 2008; Recent biographical sketches, 2001-2009; miscellaneous articles about PNCC and/or Padewski including “Rodzina” and “Commonweal,” 2005-2008. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Padewski- Naturalization paperwork, 1927; Certificate of Citizenship, 1930; Ship’s manifests, 1913; New York Times mention of death and articles, 1951; passports; Death certificate (Polish); articles, 1923-1951., 1913-1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - “Rola Ks. Biskupa Józefa Padewskiego W Walce O Prawną Stabilizację Polskiego Narodowego Kościoła Katolickiego W Kraju,” (The role of Bishop Jozef Padewski in struggle for legalization of the Polish National Catholic Church in the homeland), 2004 by Ks. Władysław Pietrzyk. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets and publications related to PNCC., 1900-2010 (Box 4A)
- Worship Sites, 1900-2009; This series contains information about PNCC parishes in the United States, Canada, Poland, and Italy.
  - Roman Catholic Churches of Polish Ethnicity in the United States- Lists, histories, and articles, 2004-2009; Polish newspapers- Dzień Polskie Parafie, 2008. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - PNCC Parishes- Massachusetts A-M., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - PNCC Parishes- Massachusetts N-Z., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - PNCC Parishes- Connecticut., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - PNCC Parishes- Maryland, Delaware, Washington D.C., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - PNCC Parishes- Wisconsin., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - PNCC Parishes- Washington., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pe Ell, Washington., 1900-2010 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - PNCC Parishes- Rhode Island; Missouri; Illinois; New Hampshire., 1900-2009 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - PNCC Parishes- New Jersey A-Ba., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - PNCC Parishes-New Jersey Bo-La., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - PNCC Parishes- New Jersey Li-Passiac., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - PNCC Parishes- New Jersey Passiac cont.-Pat., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - PNCC Parishes- New Jersey Pe-Z., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pennsylvania A-C., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pennsylvania D-F., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pennsylvania G-L., 1900-2009 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pennsylvania M-Pl., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pennsylvania Pr-Sc., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - PNCC Parishes- Pennsylvania Sh-Z & Supplement., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - PNCC Parishes- New York A-Br., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - PNCC Parishes- New York Bu-F., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - PNCC Parishes- New York G-Lan., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - PNCC Parishes- New York Lat-P., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - PNCC Parishes- New York R-Z., 1900-2009 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - PNCC Parishes- Florida; California; Texas; Colorado; North Carolina., 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - PNCC Parishes- Chicago, Illinois., 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - PNCC Parishes- Indiana; Michigan., 1900-2009 (Bin 8, Folder 3)
  - PNCC Parishes- Minnesota, Oregon., 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - PNCC Parishes- Ohio., 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - PNCC Parishes- Missouri; Iowa., 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - PNCC Parishes- International: Canada; Italy., 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - PNCC Parishes- “PNCC in Poland”, 1900-2009 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Defunct PNCC Parishes, 1904-2009; This series contains information about PNCC parishes that have been closed.
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- General information, correspondence, essays concerning defunct parish research; Pennsylvania A-Z., 1914-2008 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- New England: Connecticut; Massachusetts; New Hampshire; Rhode Island., 1930-2009 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- New Jersey A-Z (Includes essay about the Italian National Catholic Church)., 1903-2008 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- Southern states: Delaware; Florida; North Carolina; South Carolina; Texas; Virgina; West Virginia., 1928-2008 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- New York A-Z, 1931-2008. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- North West/ Midwest: Michigan; Minnesota; Ohio; Wisconsin., 1913-2008 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- Southwest: Arizona; California; Illinois; Indiana; Iowa; Washington., 1904-2008 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- International; Canada; Brazil., 1936-2009 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- Further research folder. Mention of New Jersey, New York, Massachusetts; notes., 2008 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Defunct PNCC Parishes- Red Notebook: “PNCC Defunct Parishes and Missions, Does Not Include Brazil, Italian Parishes.”, 2008-2009 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Scrapbook, 2004-2008; This series contains information about the first settlement of Polish immigrants in the United States located in Texas.
  - History of Poles in Texas., 2008 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook- Panna Maria, Texas: 150th anniversary celebration information; newsletters; information about the town, histories., 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 2)